An Inventory of the Germany (Territory under Allied occupation, 1945-1955: U.S. Zone) Office of Military Government for Bavaria. Kreis Traunstein records
Hoover Institution Archives
Germany (Territory under Allied occupation, 1945-1955: U.S. Zone) Office of Military Government for Bavaria. Kreis Traunstein records
1945-1948
XX416
Germany (Territory under Allied occupation, 1945-1955: U.S. Zone) Office of Military Government for Bavaria. Kreis Traunstein.
13 manuscript boxes (5.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The records of American administration of occupied Germany (U.S. Zone), Kreis Traunstein relating to civil administration, including problems of public health and safety, administration of justice, allocation of economic recourses, organization of labor, denazification, and disposition of displaced persons contain memoranda, reports, correspondence, and office files. The collection also presents annual administrative reports on civilian relief efforts for other districts in Bavaria.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Germany (Territory under Allied occupation, 1945-1955), Hoover Institution Archives
Germany (Territory under Allied occupation, 1945-1955: U.S. Zone) Office of Military Government Records, 1943-1950, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
The Allied powers who defeated Nazi Germany in World War II divided the country into four occupation zones for administrative purposes during the period 1945-1949. The American zone consisted of Bavaria and Hessen in Southern Germany, and the northern portions of the present-day German state of Baden-Würtemberg.
Scope and Content of Collection
The records of the American administration of occupied Germany (U.S. Zone) at Kreis Traunstein relate to the civil administration of the region. The record document problems related to public health and safety, the administration of justice, allocation of economic recourses, organization of labor, denazification, and the disposition of displaced persons. The records consist of memoranda, reports, correspondence, and office files. The collection also contains annual administrative reports on civilian relief efforts for other districts in Bavaria and miscellaneous materials of the Ukrainian Committee in Regensburg.
Arrangement
Records are arranged as originally received from the organization; generally by Office of Military Government (U.S. Zone)
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Denazification.; Military government.; Refugees.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; Bavaria (Germany)--Politics and government 1945-; Germany--History--1945-1955.; Traunstein (Germany)--Politics and government.
Collection Contents
- Office of Military Government (U.S. Zone) (OMGUS), 1945-1947 (Box 1)
  - Conference of Military Government Officers, American Zone of Occupation, Heidelberg, Germany, 1945 November (Folder 1: 1)
  - Amendment to Laws, 1945 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Land and Local Government in the U.S. Zone of Germany, by Civil Administration Division, 1947 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Analysis of Nazi Criminal Organizations, by Public Safety Branch, 1947 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Military Government Gazette, 1947 (Folder 1: 5)
- Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Force (SHAEF), 1944-1945 (Box 1-2)
  - Directives for the administration of Military Government in the U.S. Zone in Germany, 1945 (Folder 1:6)
  - Displaced persons, refugees, and welfare directives, 1944-1945 (Folder 1:7-9)
    Includes map of billeting and control facilities for displaced persons
  - Special Legal Unit of Germany and Austria, reports, 1944-1945 (Folder 1:10-13)
  - Administrative memoranda, 1944-1945 (Folder 2:1-2)
  - Technical Manual for Industry and Trade: Rationing (other then Food) and Price Control in Germany, 1945 May (Folder 2:3)
- Headquarters, U.S. Forces European Theatre (HQ USFET), 1944-1946 (Box 2)
  - Directives for the administration of Military Government in the U.S. Zone in Germany, 1945 (Folder 2:4-7)
  - Regulations, 1945 (Folder 2:8-9)
  - Office of Controller of Finance and Accounts, directives, 1944 (Folder 2:10)
  - Recurring Reports Register, 1946 (Folder 2:11)
  - Administration of Military Government in the U.S. Zone in Germany, directives, 1945 (Folder 2:12)
  - Reports and Information, instructions, 1945 (Folder 2:13)
- Headquarters 6th Army Group, G-5 Section, APO 23, U.S. Army, 1944-1945 (Box 2-3)
  - Responsibilities and Policy of the Public Safety Division, 1944-1945 (Folder 2:14)
  - Detachments reports, 1945 (Folder 2:15)
  - German Courts and prisons, 1944-1945 (Folder 3:1-2)
    Includes List of personnel in Government agencies at Traunstein
  - Financial instructions, 1945 (Folder 3:3)
  - Directives, 1945 (Folder 3:4-5)
- Headquarters, 3rd United States Army, 1945-1946 (Box 3)
  - Regulations, 1945 (Folder 3:6)
  - Wanted Prisoners of War, War Criminals and Witnesses, lists, 1945 (Folder 3:7)
  - Occupational incident reports, 1946 (Folder 3:8)
- Headquarters, 9th United States Army, Office of Commanding General, 1944-1945 (Box 3)
  - Directives, 1944-1945 (Folder 3:9)
- Office of Military Government for Bavaria (OMGB), 1943-1950 (Box 3-13)
  - Detachment G-233, Kreis Traunstein, 1943-1947 (Folder 3-4)
    - Denazification of Public Service, reports and list of persons dismissed from public employment because of former Nazi connections, 1946 (Folder 3:10-13)
    - German civilians' requests for allocation of materials and machinery, 1945-1946 (Folder 3:14-16)
    - Employment requirements and reports, 1945 (Folder 3:17)
    - Appointments, 1945 (Folder 3:18)
    - Circulars of the Ministry for Political Liberation, 1947 (Folder 3:19)
    - Price control regulations, 1945-1946 (Folder 3:20)
    - Special Industry Survey, reports, 1945 (Folder 3:21)
    - German civilians' weight and health reports, 1945-1947 (Folder 4:1-9)
    - Manpower reports, 1945 (Folder 4:10-11)
    - Daily reports, 1945-1946 (Folder 4:12)
    - Weekly reports, 1945 (Folder 4:13-17)
    - Correspondence, reports and memoranda by subject, 1945-1947 (Folder 5-8)
      - Arrests, 1945 (Folder 5:1)
      - Communicable diseases, 1945-1946 (Folder 5:2)
      - Courts, 1945-1946 (Folder 5:3-4)
      - Crime and prison, 1945-1947 (Folder 5:5)
      - Denazification, 1945-1946 (Folder 5:6)
      - Displaced persons, 1945-1946 (Folder 5:7)
      - Distribution, 1945-1946 (Folder 5:8)
      - Election, 1945-1946 (Folder 5:9)
      - Employment, 1945-1946 (Folder 5:10-15)
      - German labor, 1945-1946 (Folder 6:1-2)
        Includes Official Gazette of the Control Council for Germany, no. 4, 1946 February 28
      - Industrial, 1945 (Folder 6:3)
      - Information, 1946 (Folder 6:4)
      - Intelligence, 1945-1946 (Folder 6:5)
      - Investigations, 1945-1946 (Folder 6:6)
      - Legal affairs, 1945-1946 (Folder 6:7-9)
      - Liquor, 1946 (Folder 6:10)
      - Military travel permits, 1945-1946 (Folder 6:11-12)
      - Monthly historical reports, 1946 (Folder 6:13)
      - Payment of bills, 1946 (Folder 6:14)
      - Personnel, 1945-1946 (Folder 6:15-18)
      - Police, 1945-1946 (Folder 7:1-2)
      - Political activity, 1945-1946 (Folder 7:3)
      - Political parties, 1945-1946 (Folder 7:4)
      - Public health, 1946 (Folder 7:5)
      - Real estate, 1945-1946 (Folder 7:6)
      - Releases, 1945-1946 (Folder 7:7)
      - Requisitions, 1945-1946 (Folder 7:8-14)
      - Screening, 1946 (Folder 7:15)
      - Sport, 1946 (Folder 7:16)
      - Supplies, 1945-1946 (Folder 8:1-2)
      - Transmittals, 1945-1946 (Folder 8:3-4)
      - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration (UNRRA), 1945-1946 (Folder 8:5)
      - Vehicles, 1946 (Folder 8:6-7)
    - William Marvin, Property (Finance) Control Officer files, 1945-1946 (Folder 8:8-14)
    - Brewery operations, 1945-1946 (Folder 8:15)
    - Cigars sale, 1945 (Folder 8:16)
    - Public health directives, 1945 (Folder 9:1)
    - Orders for supplies, 1945 (Folder 9:2)
    - German civilians requests, petitions and appeals, 1943-1946 (Folder 9:3-11)
    - Lists of officials, 1945 (Folder 9:12)
    - Sanitation and public welfare, directives and reports, 1945 (Folder 9:13)
    - Lists of the employees of Public Office, showing party affiliations and dismissals, 1945 (Folder 9:14-15)
    - Fragebogen (questionnaire), 1945-1946 (Folder 9:16)
    - Fragebogen (questionnaire), 1945-1946 contd. (Folder 10:1-3)
    - Josef Keine, Landtagsabgeordnete of the Sozialdemokratische Partei Deutschlands (SPD), Upper Bavaria, 1946-1948 (Folder 10:4-8)
      Includes correspondence, memoranda, lists and clippings,
    - Michael Utzmeier, military documents, 1935-1945 (Folder 10:9)
    - Frederich-Wilhelm Posnien, Frontalier Permit, 1946-1948 (Folder 10:10)
  - Table of organization, 1947 January (Folder 10:11)
  - List of communities, circa 1945 (Folder 10:12)
  - Youth hostels, location and capacity, circa 1945 (Folder 10:13)
  - Statistical News, no.12, bulletin, Economic Division, 1946 (Folder 10:14)
  - 3 Aastat Geislingenis, albumi koostaja, in Estonian, 1948 (Folder 11:1)
  - Public safety regulations, 1945 (Folder 11:2)
  - Field Operation Division, Area Offices Annual Historical Report, 1948 (Folder 11-12)
    - Amberg (Folder 11:3-4)
    - Ansbach (Folder 11:5)
    - Augsburg (Folder 11:6-7)
    - Bad Kissingen (Folder 11:8)
    - Bamberg (Folder 11:9)
    - Bayreuth (Folder 11:10)
    - Coburg (Folder 11:11-12)
    - Eggenfelden (Folder 11:13)
    - Erlangen (Folder 11:14)
    - Friesing (Folder 11:15)
    - Hof (Folder 12:1-2)
    - Garmisch (Folder 12:3)
    - Ingolstadt (Folder 12:4)
    - Kempten (Folder 12:5-6)
    - Kitzingem (Folder 12:7)
    - Miesbach (Folder 12:8)
    - München (Folder 12:9)
    - Nürnberg (Folder 12:10)
    - Passau (Folder 12:11-12)
    - Regensberg (Folder 12:13-15)
    - Regensberg (contd.), 1946-1950 (Folder 13:1-6)
      Includes miscellany materials of Ukrainian Committee in Regensburg,
    - Rosenheim (Folder 13:7-8)
    - Straubing (Folder 13:9)
    - Tölz (Folder 13:10)
    - Vilshofen (Folder 13:11)